We sent him to a third country, an
extraordinary
rendition, and he broke in two days, and
spilled
everything. I have no idea what they did
to him. And when I asked
jokingly, one of their officers, he
said, "Oh, we gave him a cup of tea and
an offer he couldn't
refuse." And that that's all he would
say.
How can I help? How can I be useful in
ending needless suffering? Do not be
afraid of work that has no end.
We have to organize a social movement.
We have an opportunity to lead by
example versus just talking hot
air. I think the more people in this
fight, the more we grow. Eventually, it
could change. You the people are the
ones that can make the change.
Ladies and gentlemen, welcome back. Hope
you're ready for another episode of
Change Agents, an ironcloud original
presented by Firecracker Farm. Now,
let's dive in.
The first question, of course, is going
to be, how the hell did you find your
way to working for the Central
Intelligence Agency? Well, I I had a
very nontraditional
uh entry into the CIA. Actually, the way
I made it into the CIA is actually
illegal now uh because of passage of the
Equal Employment Opportunity Act. But um
I was in grad
school. I was in grad school at George
Washington University and I was taking a
class called the psychology of
leadership. Loved this class. Taught by
an eminent psychiatrist named Jerry
Post, Dr. Gerald Post. and
um he assigned us a paper where we had
to shadow our bosses for a week and then
write a psychological profile of our
bosses, like a deep psychological dive.
I was working at a union at the time
called the United Food and Commercial
Workers Union, second largest union
within the AFL CIO next to the
Teamsters. And um and my boss was this
old school
mean like he he had had his back broken
by scabs during a during a riot, you
know, at a strike and just a mean old
man. And I was shadowing him this this
week and uh and on Wednesday, halfway
through the week, we got into an
argument and I called him a racist,
which he was. And he got so mad he put
up his fists and and I I put up my hands
because I thought, "Oh, I went too far
this time." I put up my hands and he
goes, "My penis is bigger than yours."
And I said,
"What?" And he goes, "My penis is bigger
than yours." And I said, "You know what?
You're nuts." And I quit. And I walked
out. So I had already accumulated a
shitload of of data from my paper. And
um I went back home. I wrote the paper,
I passed it in and uh and a week later I
got the paper back and I got an A, but
in the margin Dr. Post had written,
"Please see me after class." So I went
to see him and I said, "Dr. Post, you
wanted to see me." And he said,
"Listen," he closes the door. He goes,
"Listen, I'm not really a professor
here. I'm a CIA officer undercover as a
professor here, and I'm looking for
people who might fit into the CIA's
culture." I think you would fit into the
CIA's culture. Do you want to be a CIA
officer? And I said
yes. And you know, the rest was up to
me. I had to pass the polygraph. I had
to get through the background
investigation. You know, they have
medical stuff and all kinds of crazy
[__] that they make you do. Um, but I
but I made it and it was thanks to Jerry
Post. He was a spotter. Isn't there
wouldn't there be a better way to ask
somebody that question as opposed to
putting all your cards on the table and
just saying I am not a teacher. I am a
CIA recruiter. I feel like if you say
that to the wrong person, the word might
get out if you know what I mean. Yeah.
But you know what though? It's similar
to recruiting an agent uh when you're an
officer in the field where you don't
make the pitch unless you are 100%
certain they're going to say yes. That's
how you protect yourself in the field.
You you carry that relationship all the
way to the end. Unless, of course,
you're trying to to frighten the target,
you know, into doing something or not
doing something, but you you sort of
save the pitch for for when you're
certain the answer is going to be yes.
Do you think that the school was aware
of what he was doing? Oh, absolutely.
Absolutely. This was this was outlawed
of course in in 93 with passage of the
EEOC, but the agency's gotten around
that by Yeah, I was gonna say there's a
lot of things that are outlawed. It
doesn't necessarily mean they stop.
Yeah. So, what they do now, it's it's
actually quite funny. It's it's called
the uh scholar and residence program.
So what they do is let's say let's say
you are two years from retirement and
they come up to you and they say uh so
what are your plans for retirement? You
say I think I'm going to go back home to
Pittsburgh. They say how about this for
an
idea. We send you to the University of
Pittsburgh where you are the CIA scholar
in residence. You teach one class
called espionage in Soviet
literature and what you really do is you
act as a spotter. But because you're
overtly CIA, students know, hey, I can
go to that professor and the professor
can call recruiting and say, "Hey, I've
got a good one for you." And you just
turn it over to recruiting. So, it's all
in the in the in the open. It's not
clandestine like it used to be, but you
still get the same job done.
Interesting. Well, I know we'll talk
about uh you know, the delicious center
of the Oreo of your career. Let's talk
about the other Let's talk about the
other wafer. Why did you decide to
leave?
I wish I could tell you
that, you know, I stood on my principles
and I told them that wasn't it at all. I
had just gotten divorced. I had two
little boys. They were nine and
six.
And you know, kids need their fathers.
And so my ex-wife moved back to
Ohio. And
um I tell you, I my career was really
surging at the time. I I had become I
had just captured Abu Zubeta and I'd
become the executive assistant to the
CIA's deputy director for
operations. So this is an important job.
He offered me three station chief
positions and I said, you know, I'd
rather I'd rather go to the United
Nations. And he said, oo, that that's
really not career enhancing. And I said,
I know, but I still have 20 years ahead
of me. I can be a station chief, you
know, when my kids are old enough. So, I
went to the UN and I just decided, this
is untenable because we're still at war
in Iraq. We're still at war in
Afghanistan. We're having to recycle
back in. I had to volunteer like they
they were requesting volunteers and if
they there weren't enough by God they
were going to send all of us back. So I
volunteered to go back to Iraq again and
I said I got remarried. I said to my my
wife that this is untenable and so I
resigned. I went into the p to the
private sector and I
drove every other weekend from
Washington to Ohio for 11 years and I
never missed a weekend.
That's awesome. It was important.
Yeah, I couldn't agree more. I actually
have uh been through a divorce as well
and my children were at this point six
years younger than they are now. So
getting into their teens and my daughter
was barely just crouching into uh double
digits and yeah, that's what you have to
do and you have to sacrifice everything
else. That's it. You're exactly right.
Yeah.
So it sounds like I mean I think if
people if they Google your name, you're
going to find a bunch of things about
the agency. One of the main things that
comes up though is your whistleblowing
on water boarding. Mhm. And I'm curious,
although like you said, you didn't stand
directly on your morals, and honestly, I
think the number of times that that
actually happens that cleanly and
precisely, that's more of a Hallmark
movie type thing. In my own experience,
it's You're right. It's shades of slices
of an onion. Yeah. They much over time.
Yes. Yeah. Yeah. I wish life was that uh
pristine. It's easier to box it into 44
minutes of TV and 16 minutes of
commercials, but it just hasn't been my
experience in life. I think you're
exactly right. The waterboarding
Yeah. The waterboarding aspect
specifically, which I will note that
they used to do to us for fun and I'm
still upset about that. We did the same
in training. It was awful. Yeah. Yeah.
And I and I also think we got a light
version of it. I mean, I have uh I've
never witnessed it in person at uh an
enhanced
interrogation site. Uh they gave us a
version, you know, a lighter one at the
advanced SEIR schools. It sucked for
sure. I mean, you get an understanding
of it.
What uh what got you to the point where
you were willing to openly discuss
waterboarding and the enhanced
interrogations? Well, you see, this is
another one of those situations where I
wish I could say that I stood on my
principles and I told them and again
that wasn't it.
I will say that
my my transition
to the human rights guy, which was my my
nickname behind my back uh in the the
counterterrorism center uh came
incrementally and it started the night
that we captured
Abazuba. So, a couple of nights later,
we we captured so many guys that night,
al-Qaeda guys, that we had to bring them
to our safe house in shifts in a patty
wagon to interrogate
them 10 at a time. And
so, there was this [__] idiot who
worked for me. His dad was a an agency
big shot, but but the son never made it
through ops training. He just flunked
out. So, they made him what's called a
sue, a special operations officer, which
means that they're like the assistants
to the to the ops guys, like, "Hey, fill
out my paperwork or put together a
surveillance team and make sure I'm not
being followed or whatever." You know,
they don't actually go out there doing
operations. So, this
idiot was on loan to me and um he brings
a group of prisoners in and they all
have hoods on and I said, "Why do they
have hoods on? And he said, "We don't
want him to see our faces." And I go,
"Are you seriously telling me that you
have never read the Geneva Convention?
Seriously, hooding a prisoner is a war
crime. Take the hoods off." And a couple
of his guys go to grab the hood. And he
goes, "Wait, wait, leave the hoods on."
He goes, "I'm going to report you to
headquarters." I said, "Oh, I'm already
reporting you to headquarters for
committing a war crime. Take the [__]
hoods off." And so they took the hoods
off. We reported each other and I got
ripper.
[Laughter]
I'm going to have tell on you. [__] you.
I already told on you. Yeah. And I I
thought, oh, okay. So, this is how we're
going to play. All right. We're just
going to pretend these laws don't exist
because we're the good guys. And
so, like I say, it it
was
incremental. Like, I can see Listen, I
wanted revenge for 9/11 just like
everybody else did. I wanted to kill
these guys. I told Abu Zuba, I should
want to kill you. I don't I should, but
I don't. But, you know, we're supposed
to be the good guys, and the good guys
follow the rule of law, whether we like
it or not. And, you know, there was
there was even more to that. It was it
was in
1946 we executed Japanese soldiers who
had waterboarded American PS. That was a
death penalty offense to waterboard
somebody. On January 11th,
1968, the Washington Post ran a front
page photograph of an American soldier
waterboarding a North Vietnamese
prisoner. Robert McNamera was the was
the Secretary of Defense. He ordered an
investigation that day. The soldier was
arrested. He was charged with torture.
He was convicted and sentenced to 20
years of hard labor at
Levvenworth. And then in 2002, like
magic, it's all
legal. Well, the law never changed. The
law was never amended. Congress never
voted to repeal it or to amend it. we
just decided because we're the good
guys, we're going to do this now and
we're just going to say it's legal. And
that wasn't good enough for me. And so,
yeah, starting with the hooding and then
going through the torture and water
boarding was not the worst. You know,
there were others. The cold cell, we we
killed people using the cold cell. You
know, you chain the guy to an eyebolt in
the ceiling, you strip him naked, you
you chill the cell down to 50 degrees
Fahrenheit, and then you throw a bucket
of ice water on him every every hour. We
killed people with that with that. Add a
fan to that situation. That's as cold as
you're ever going to get. You're exactly
right. Well, the Justice Department, I
read the I read the classified uh uh uh
what do you call it from the Justice
Department, the uh recommendation, but
uh they never said we could kill
people. Another one was sleep
deprivation. I I did a contract with the
American Psychological Association um
after I got out. It was to we came up
with something called the Brookline
Protocols, which were the new rules for
APA members involved in u in uh national
security interrogations.
Sleep
deprivation. We know from the
APA that you begin to lose your mind at
day seven with no sleep. You begin to
die from organ failure at day nine with
no sleep. But the CIA was authorized to
keep people awake for 12 days. And
people die doing that, too. You're
chained to that same eyebolt. You have
the the music on loop, you know, at the
the volume of 11 and uh and the the
military strength lights on you all the
time and you die of organ failure. It's
like, how's that legal? The Justice
Department never said we could start
murdering
people. So, I
objected.
how I mean I I have interfaced with the
agency mostly from a case officer
perspective overseas. Um and one thing I
hear from people often they'll say they
want to they kind of want to denounce
the agency and I always try to remind
people that any agency or organization
is comprised of people and you're
probably better off exercising the
cancer as opposed to radiating the whole
body. That's right. But but inside of
Yeah. inside of the agency when it came
to those enhanced interrogation
authorizations. I mean, was this is this
an open secret? Was this very closely
guarded? Oh, it was very very tightly
held. In fact, when I was first
approached,
um I was asked if I wanted to be trained
in these enhanced interrogation
techniques. I was told that only 16
people in the CIA knew that this program
existed.
16 people.
That's a lot tighter than I would have
thought. Yeah, it was very tight.
Do you think Well, and there's an aspect
of this we have to add as well, too. I
mean, there's a rendition program.
There's the reality that the United
States when they don't want to get their
fingernails super dirty, like I don't
know what's going over in Egypt or
Jordan or other countries that have
extra car batteries and uh nipple
clamps. Not I mean that's more of a
movie more of a movie thing than
anything. But yeah, you'd be surprised.
Well, and that's and that's the issue. I
mean, it's it's funny when people
actually start to look for these things.
It's not even that well hidden. I
remember I the rendition program. I used
to uh fly Gulf Streams after I got out
of the military. That's cool. There was
a Gulf Stream that went up for sale and
for whatever reason it got associated
with the agency cuz it was one of their
birds that they were using for rendition
which got me down this rabbit hole of
looking more at that rendition program.
So the again the information is out
there. It's more just a matter of people
having access to it. That's what piqu my
interest. Do you think it actually ever
stopped? Because it's the same thing
as you know the agency from my
understanding is supposed to be
externally oriented but they'll use
cutouts they'll use corporations largely
formed by ex employees or they'll create
a paramilitary arm right the ground
branch the air branch the maritime
branch all of these things right do you
think it ever actually stopped or do
they just keep finding taking left and
right turns until they can get to the
end state that they want and justify it
that way I don't think rendition
or extraordinary rendition ever stopped.
I don't think it it even slowed. Um and
certainly Congress has never acted on
it. And you know, we should we should
point out to your viewers too that
there's a difference between a rendition
and an extraordinary rendition. If I'm
in Pakistan and I catch you and you're
from Tunisia and I send you back to
Tunisia, that's a rendition.
An extraordinary rendition is if I'm in
Pakistan and I catch you and you're from
Tunisia and I send you to Egypt or Syria
or you can dress in a diaper with a
suppository to knock you out and you're
handcuffed and you wake up in Egypt.
Exactly. Now, there's
nothing that's specifically illegal
there. I mean, you could argue that it's
kidnapping, but it's a crime that has
that was not committed on US soil and it
was done, you know, in the name of the
government and it was done to address a
clear and present
danger. So, I don't think that there was
ever even a slowdown in
renditions. And I and listen, I don't
want to sound like a I don't I don't
want to sound like a hypocrite,
but and there have certainly been well
doumented horrible horrible mistakes
with renditions. Yeah. But
philosophically, I don't have a problem
with renditions.
I don't. I have to agree with you on
that just based on my again my own
experience. I mean, we're you had saw a
different side of the coin than I did. I
saw more of the the tactical
perspective, largely based off of
information that would come from sources
such as yourself. It's
it's as if you're trying to walk on top
of a razor blade without getting cut.
And I and I don't know if it's possible.
And I can sit here and say yes, I saw
extreme benefit from it and sometimes
the ends justified the means. But I can
also say that sometimes the wrong people
got wrapped up and I have no idea where
they went or what the impact was to
their life. And I don't know, maybe
that's a a never- ending existential
question that you have to ask yourself
or that's something you have to confront
on your deathbed.
Yeah. For the right person, for the
right reasons, I can't necessarily say I
have an issue with the rendition either.
Yeah. Yeah. I'm I'm going to speak very
uh circumspectly, but there there was a
guy in whenever I think of renditions, I
think of this this
case. I I received a cable from
headquarters. I was in Pakistan saying
that that a really bad guy was going to
arrive uh in Karach. So I alerted my
liaison uh contacts. I flew down to
Karach. We grabbed the guy at the
airport and um and we took him back to
Islamabad and I began interrogating him.
He did
everything in the al-Qaeda training
manual. He pretended to pass out and he
fell off the chair. He pretended to have
an excruciating pain in his stomach and
we would just sit there and look at him
like this like, "Are you
done?" And he had his cover story down.
Pat, he just kept repeating it over and
over. We knew none of it was true
because he didn't know that, you know,
what we knew from the previous several
weeks. And
um and finally I said to him,
"Look, you're making this really hard.
Not for us, cuz I don't give a [__] one
way or the other, but for yourself." And
he goes, "I'm not afraid of you. I'm not
afraid of anything you can do to me."
And I said, "I don't expect you to be
afraid." I said, "Our partners though,
our partners are going to make sure that
you're afraid."
We sent him to a third country, an
extraordinary
rendition, and he broke in two days, and
spilled
everything. I have no idea what they did
to him. And when I asked
jokingly, one of their officers, he
said, "Oh, we gave him a cup of tea and
an offer he couldn't
refuse." And that that's all he would
say.
I wonder if his uh penis was in a vice
while he was having that cup of tea.
Perhaps that was the offer he
Exactly. Exactly.
Man, that's almost one where it's like,
I don't know if I want to ask you this
question.
Yeah. Yeah. We offered him a cup of tea.
It's like, wow.
Ladies and gentlemen, you've heard me
talk about Firecracker Farm and their
hot soul. You probably heard other
people talk about it as well. If you
haven't tried it yet, let me just tell
you, you're missing out on some serious
flavor. Their hot salt is delicious, and
it really makes pretty much anything
that you put it on even more delicious.
It's hot, but when you use it in
moderation, it's not too hot, and the
flavor that it adds enhances without
overpowering. It is handmade, super
premium, and comes in awesome stainless
steel push button grinders like the one
I have in my hand right here. You can
take them anywhere. Hot sauce, if you've
had this experience, can very easily
overpower other flavors and always runs
out quickly when it's good. Hot salt
lasts and lasts. The Push Grinder holds
over 500 plus pumps, and when you
consider the refill it comes with, it's
thousands of servings, and it's a great
deal and a lot cheaper than the sauce.
For those of you that like flavor, but
hesitate because it might be too hot,
you can mix it with sea salt to tone it
down and still enjoy the awesome flavor.
In my personal experience, you can
modulate how much comes out of the
dispenser. You're in total control of
the amount of heat you serve yourself.
So, if you would like to support our
show and give Alex and his family
business a shot, head over to
firecracker.farm and use the code
ironcloud to get a 15% discount on your
first order. You will be very glad that
you did. Firecracker.comfarm.
You know, it was uh on a television show
when you first mentioned waterboarding,
correct? Yes. Yes. It was uh an
interview with Brian Ross on ABC News.
What was it about that day? Why then?
Oh, I can tell you exactly what it was.
Brian Ross had called
me about a week and a half earlier and I
had never spoken to a journalist before,
so I didn't know the little tricks that
journalists use. So he calls me and he
says he's Brian Ross from ABC News,
famous guy. So I knew exactly who he
was. And he said that he had a source
who said that I had tortured Abu Zuba. I
said that was absolutely untrue. I never
laid a hand on Abu Zuba. I never laid a
hand on anybody else. I said, in fact, I
was the only person who was kind to Abu
Zuba. And like I say, I don't I didn't
know these reporters tricks. He says,
"Well, you're welcome to come on the
show and defend
yourself." I said, "I'll think about
it." Yeah. In the meantime, a couple of
days later, President Bush gives a press
conference. And
um there was a reporter at the press
conference who asked him about um about
these reports that come had come out
from human rights organizations. Amnesty
International, Human Rights Watch, uh
the Red Cross, they had all said
publicly that the CIA was torturing
prisoners. So this reporter asks Bush
about these reports and Bush looks in
the camera and he goes, "We do not
torture my wife and I." My wife was a
senior CIA officer. We're sitting on the
couch and I said, "He's a bald-faced
liar. He's just looking the American
people right in the eye and he's lying
to
them." And then two days later, well,
that would be the first time in the
history of a politician doing that.
Yeah, exactly. Shocking.
Shocking. Where do we go from here? Um,
so yeah, two days later was a Friday,
Bush comes out of the South Portico of
the White House to get on a helicopter
to go to Camp David for the weekend. A
reporter shouts a question at him and he
turns and he says, "Well, if there is
torture, it's because of a rogue CIA
officer." And I said to my wife,
"They're going to try to pin this on
me." So I said, "Brian Rosson sources at
the White House and they're going to pin
this on me." So I called him. I said,
"I'll give you your interview." And I
decided in the whatever it was, four
days, five days between that call and
the interview, that I would just tell
the truth or the truth as I knew it. And
so that's what I did.
Uh we probably neither you or I ever
breathed the air where the actual
decisions were made or conversations
were had. Yeah. Yeah. Do you think it's
even possible or plausible that Bush
didn't know exactly what the agency was
up to? You know what? That's a great
question. And
until until 10 years ago, I would have
said, "No, not possible." But then
George Tennant wrote something in his
memoir that was just stupifying.
He said
that he had taken the um the finding,
the draft
finding to create the torture program to
the White House. And he was going in to
have the president sign the finding. But
Dick Cheney was in the anti- room and he
says, "Oh, hi George. What are you doing
here?" And he said, "Oh, I've got the
finding, the the finished finding. I'm
here for the president's signature." And
uh Cheney took it from him and said,
"I'll get the president to sign it." And
um George said, "No, that's okay. I
already have the appointment." Cheney
said, "No, I'll get the president to
sign it." So George gave Cheney the
finding and went back to headquarters.
George said in whatever it was, 2016 or
whenever his memoir came out, that he
finally concluded that either Cheney
never showed the president the finding
or just asked for his signature without
telling him what it was. And so when
Bush claimed ignorance, you know, we all
mocked him. Like what kind of [__]
thinks that the American people would
believe that the president of the United
States didn't know that this program was
ongoing? You know what? I'm thinking
that the man didn't know. I think that
Cheney kept it from him.
Yeah, I can see I could see both of
those being true. I I can 100% see the
argument being made from a politician.
Well, we need to insulate the president.
we'll make these decisions and then
we'll brief him when necessary because
then if he's called to the table on it,
he's not going to necessarily be
responsible. That's right. And even in
the Navy, you know, like the SEAL
community is part of a larger Navy. It's
like
0.0001% of Right. the Navy. the chief,
you know, the the most senior naval
admiral, which I don't think comes from
the spec war community, isn't going to
have necessarily oversight of all the
cover programs that may exist inside of
the Navy, but yet they are responsible
for them to a degree. So, I can see
that. God, it's fascinating if you look
into how much power chain he had inside
of the Bush White House and how, you
know, it's it's really crazy. Yeah. to
think there was this this uh movie that
came out I don't know eight or 10 years
ago called Vice. Um Oh, I saw it. Yeah,
I saw it on plane. Yes.
He was brilliant. I saw it on a plane
and I was like, "Oh my god, they they
hit this on the head." This this was
Dick Cheney. They really hit it on the
head. The man was president. He was in
charge of everything. And that was the
deal that he struck with Bush. You know,
Bush had this bad habit of asking people
to head up, you know, blue ribbon panels
or whatever to make a recommendation on
personnel and then he would just choose
the head of the blue ribbon panel
instead of the person that they
recommended. He did that with Harriet
Meyers for for the Supreme Court and
then she ended up having to withdraw.
But he did that as well with Dick
Cheney. He asked Cheney, "Find me a vice
president." Cheney gave him three or
four names and then he said, "No, no,
I'd rather have you." Well, Mr. uh
Governor Bush, if if uh you want me, I
want to be char in charge of foreign
affairs, defense affairs, intelligence,
energy, this one, that one, the other
one.
Okay. And then that was it. The great
scene in the movie. Yeah. Backyard over
lunch. Great. I have no doubt that that
was true.
[__] You don't want to believe that
that is how the people who turn the
levers of power or move the levers of
power are selected. Oh, buddy. Listen,
let me tell you. I don't want to believe
that's the case. Yeah. Let me let me
tell you. I I used to go on the Tucker
Carlson show all the time when he was on
Fox and
um we were talking about John Brennan
one time and I took a swipe at Brennan
deservedly. I said Brennan was in over
his head uh
intellectually. Well, I didn't say that
to be mean. I said that because I've
known John Brennan for 35 years and I'm
telling you the man was in over his head
intellectually. Well, there are a lot of
people like that in government. Just
because you're successful at clawing
your way to the top on the backs of the
people around you doesn't make you the
smartest person in the room. It makes
you a sociopath, but it doesn't make you
the smartest person in the room. And we
got that all the time.
Yeah. Yeah, I almost think that's the uh
the political ladder. It's almost the
template for the political ladder. It's
not it's not the people who are the most
benevolent who are want I don't know. I
actually kicked this one around in my
head. Is it the sociopath that wants to
be a politician or is the system so
toxic and polluted that it can turn the
most benevolent among us? They see like
I can't do anything unless I line on
party lines.
Uh either way, neither of those are a
great answer. No, but but you know what?
Very well could be something to that. I
worked with a guy I was I was mentor to
a young uh uh case officer named Will
Herd. So Will was around for I don't
know eight or 10 years. He was a good
case officer.
Um he's half black, half white, which is
important because he decided to resign
from the agency and run for
Congress. and he ran in a Supreme Court
mandated majority Hispanic district.
It's the 23rd district of Texas. It goes
all along the border. Just follows the
border. And he won. And he won three
times. The Supreme Court made this
district so that a Hispanic could get
elected. Most likely a Democrat because
there are more more registered Democrats
than Republicans there. And Will is a
moderate Republican and he won three
times. And we we joked with him when he
first announced. We're like, "Will,
Congress is not a step up. You're making
a mistake. You don't want to be with
these guys." He ran. He won. He starts
writing bills on cyber security. Even
with Democrats in power, they're getting
passed into law. And then after three
terms, he quit. And he's like, "This is
[__] I can't do this anymore. The
system is rigged to fail. And so now
he's on the board of Chat GPT and he's
the he's on the board of a bunch of
things, but Chat GPT is where he's
really making his money now. He ran for
president for a minute. Uh but that
didn't didn't do anything for him. But
you know what? The country's is a lesser
place because people like Will would
rather just walk away knowing that they
can't overcome the system that we've
given ourselves.
Yeah. Or it's evolved into for sure.
Yeah. Or it's evolved into.
Yeah. That's right. I'm Katarina
Schultz. I'm a relentless investigative
journalist who spent the last few years
embedded in the heart of chaos of the
world's most dangerous drug war. Here is
a deadline. You might have heard my
reporting on borderland narcosis. Now
I'm taking you to the front
lines. I've built trust on both sides
with traffickers, law enforcement, and
the very people trapped in between. I'm
taking you into the heart of Mexico's
cartel
war with fast raw updates from the heart
of the
borderlands. Subscribe now to Borderland
Dispatches with me, Katarina Schultz,
and don't miss my regular appearances on
Borderland Narcosis with Vince Roco
Vargas on YouTube at This is Ironclad or
wherever you get your podcasts.
when uh how swift so you were out of the
agency at the time when you did that
interview, correct? Yes. How swift was
the response and what was it? Ah, that's
a great question. Um, so and it's
actually kind of a complicated answer.
So the very next day after the
interview, the CIA filed what's called a
crimes report against me, telling the
FBI that I had uh revealed top secret
information uh to the public. So the FBI
interviewed me from dis interviewed me
the FBI investigated me from December of
'07 to December of '08 and then they
sent my attorneys a declination letter
declining to prosecute me because they
said that it's illegal to classify a
crime for the purpose of keeping the
information from the American people.
They believed torture was a crime, so
it's not a prosecutable offense. It was
im improperly
classified. My wife and I went out to
dinner that night to celebrate. Three
weeks later, Barack Obama becomes
president. John Brennan becomes the
deputy national security adviser for
counterterrorism. Like I said a minute
ago, John and I always hated each other.
John was, you know, his democratic uh uh
bonafites uh aside, uh John was was one
of the godfathers of the torture
program. He was the executive director
of the CIA, the third ranking official
in the CIA during the pro the program.
So, I had no
idea that on January
21st of
2009, Brennan asked the Justice
Department to secretly reopen the case
against me. And so, they investigated me
for three more years until January of
2012. and they finally charged me with
five felonies, three counts of
espionage for the for the interview with
uh with ABC and a subsequent interview I
gave to uh the New York Times. Um and
then two lesser
accounts. One was making a false
statement and we were never quite sure
exactly what the false statement was
supposed to have been, but what they did
is they knew I hadn't committed
espionage. So they waited until I went
bankrupt 10 months later and then they
dropped the espionage
charges. So I ended up taking
Yeah. So I ended up taking a plea to a
lesser count. I got 23 months in
prison and
um and did
it actually today today is what? Tuesday
that we're recording this. Correct. I
I'm in the process of applying this
morning for a for a presidential pardon.
I have so much wonderful support in the
Trump administration. It humbles me. And
so I even got down to Mara Lago and I
had, you know, 10 seconds with the man.
And so I I'm hoping that I can I can
push this through.
It's amazing to hear those stories of
again the government is such I mean
hundreds of thousands of
employees and one person can direct
Yeah. the intensity in power of a US
entity like the FBI. How crazy is that?
And there's no accident Yeah. There's no
accident that they pushed you to the
point where you were bankrupt. They put
you into a position. And if I if I may,
if you if you don't mind humoring me for
one second, I want to pull up a uh you
know what? I I I have it on my phone. I
want to pull up an email that I
received not long ago
uh that that really put things into
perspective for me. Give me one second.
And here it
is. Dear John, it's so nice to finally
speak with you. I've been watching your
YouTube interviews and I love all the
content and I've been wanting to reach
out to you for many years. I'm one of
the FBI agents who would like to
personally apologize to you for the
disgraceful way that the FBI and our
government treated you. I worked with
both headquarters and the Washington
field office team on your case and I
know all of the personnel that you're
familiar with. That case was directed
and driven by seniormost officials. Many
mid-level and street level personnel
were against it, but nevertheless, we
just followed orders. Anyway, I've
always felt bad about what we did to you
and I feel bad for the way you and your
family were treated and I wanted to
personally apologize sincerely. And then
he signs it.
That's the third one that I've gotten
since my conviction.
The third one. It's a great email. It's
a great email. And part of me says,
"Awesome for that person sending that."
But but another part of me says, "Fuck
you. You should have stopped following
orders. You're exactly right." Yeah.
Yeah. Do you
think, you know, you're talking about
Brennan and him being one of the
architects of the uh enhanced
interrogation program? Do you think that
they had that thing on the shelf and
they were just waiting for a time to
institute it or did they create that
program post 911? Yeah, they created it
immediately post 911. So the way that
that senior officials told me was that
in October there was a dinner party and
all the big mucky mucks from the CIA
were at this dinner party and one of the
leaders of the CIA's counterterrorism
center brought
um uh James Mitchell and Bruce Jessen,
the two uh contract psychologists to the
party and introduced them to George
Tennant saying these These guys are both
um uh national security uh
psychologists. They've come up with a
program that you're really going to need
to hear about. And so that's how the
whole thing started. It started around
the 11th or 12th of October 2001. And
then by January, they were ready to go.
They were just waiting for us to catch
the first high-value target. And then
in the first week of February 2002, we
were told that Abu Zubedo was in
Pakistan and I was tasked with capturing
him. Took us six weeks, but we we
tracked him down. We had no idea that
this program was awaiting him.
Wow. It's amazing they were able to do
that that quickly. Oh man, it was hard.
I never worked so hard in my entire
life.
Oh, I bet. Yeah, that was a that was an
odd time for sure. Talk about going from
a conceptual job to a very practical
job. Oh my god. Going from first sleep
under your desk. Oh yeah. You you you
sleep under your desk two hours at a
time. I would wake up some mornings and
just not remember where I was. Like
where where am I? Oh yeah, I'm in Queda.
Oh, what am I doing in Queta? Oh yeah,
that's right. I got to catch this guy
today. You know, it's crazy. It's
interesting hearing you. Yeah. Well, I
mean, I've tried to explain this to my
children. The the feeling in the
country, and I'll call it 72 to 96 hours
from 9/11 after, I have never felt a
more connected, congealed society that
everybody pretty much put their [__]
aside. Everybody. And and you know,
hearing you talk about sleeping under
your desk. I mean, there were so many
people
that that gave so much to try to orient
our country into at least a protective
posture and then an aggressive posture.
And I'm curious your thoughts because my
thoughts have radically shifted to I've
been out of the military since 2010. Did
about 10 years of deployments in the
post GWAT era and now the whole, you
know, the GWAT era, the GWAT veteran era
has rounded itself up a little bit. Mhm.
And I have conversations with uh friends
of mine, many of them who dedicated far
more of their life than myself in that
direction. And it's interesting to hear
our shifting thoughts about how
passionate we were when everything first
started. And now how we feel about the
energy and sacrifices personally and
professionally that we put in looking
back on it now. And I'm curious just
your thoughts looking back on that 20
year period, call it from, you know,
2001 to 2021.
What are your thoughts on it now? Where
do you think our country is is in a
better place? Going from that place of
sleeping under your desk to 20 years
after that, did we [__] it up even more?
We may have. Yeah. I think that if if
you're comparing apples to apples, I
think we probably are safer today, but
it's cost us $2 trillion.
Uh and I think where it really began to
turn was uh the decision to attack Iraq.
You know, I remember my my very first
day when when I got back from Pakistan,
I I was named um uh chief of counter
intelligence for the uh it was called
Alex Station. It was the Osama bin Laden
unit. So my my job was to try to root
out u potential moles, al-Qaeda moles
trying to infiltrate uh either the
United States or American embassies
abroad. And I was only in that job for
six weeks. And uh and the deputy
director asked that I become his
executive
assistant. In that
job, you have access to literally
everything that the CIA is doing around
the world. So on my and and there there
were three of us. He had three executive
assistants each focusing on a different
thing. So I was counterterrorism and
Iraq. I didn't know I was Iraq at the
time. So my first day uh this was in
um June June 1st of uh
O2. So I uh I go to the office and I
said I go like this. I said, "So what
are we doing?" And he says, "I can't
tell you. You have to go to the sixth
floor and sign a whole bunch of secrecy
agreements." And I said, ' Okay. So, I
go to the sixth floor and uh knock on
the guy's door. I knew the guy. I had
known him for years. I said, "Hey." He
said, "Hey, I've got your secrecy
agreements here." So, I signed there was
six of them. He had them all laid out on
a table. So, I signed all six of them.
And I said, "Okay, what's up?"
and he says,
"Well, next
year in February, we're going to attack
Iraq. We're going to overthrow Saddam
Hussein, and we're going to open the
world's largest air force base so that
we can move all of our air assets out of
Saudi Arabia and deprive Osama bin Laden
of his ability to say that we're
polluting the land of the two holy
mosques."
And I was dumbfounded. And I said, "But
but we haven't captured Bin Laden yet."
And he said, "Buddy, the decision's
already been made. They don't want to
hear our opinions." And I said, "Okay."
I said, "So what's the background?" And
he said, "There are clear battle lines
here." He said the pro-invasion groups
are OVP, the Office of the Vice
President, OSD, the Office of the
Secretary of Defense, and the Joint
Chiefs. I'm sorry, uh the uh National
Security Council. He said, "The anti-war
group are the Joint Chiefs, the CIA, and
the State
Department." And he said, "But we've
been overruled. The decisions been made,
and we've got to support the policy.
So, I went back to the deputy director's
office and he said, 'You sign
everything?' And I said, 'Yeah.' And he
said, "Pretty crazy, right?" And I said,
"Yeah, this is pretty
crazy." And then we started gearing up
for the Iraq
war.
Yeah, I feel like that decision, the OVP
had a heavy hand in that to go back to
the movie that we both watched and
enjoyed so much. He really did. And I'll
tell you another thing. I've told this
story in podcasts a couple of times, but
it bears a repeating here. The night
before we invaded Iraq, we had a there
was a principal committee meeting. So
the principal committee is normally
chaired by the president, and uh it's
got the secretary of state, the
secretary of defense, the national
security adviser, the CIA director. Um
they'll invite a handful of other
seriously high level people, principles.
Um, for whatever
reason, Cheney was chairing the meeting
this day. So, I was the notetaker for
George Tennant. We were in his secure
video uh teleconference room. I'm
sitting directly behind him taking
notes. And that's all my job was to sit
silently and take notes. So, Cheney is
chairing the meeting. We got all these
video screens, right? So it's Cheney,
Connie Rice, Rumsfeld,
uh General Franks from SenCom,
uh Colin Powell was
on, a couple guys from the NSC, and
us. And uh Cheney says, "General Franks,
why don't you start with the order of
battle?" And I've said a couple times, I
always hate orders of battle because the
CIA doesn't give a [__] about the order
of battle. you know, this group is here
and this one's moving there and with
elements of the fourth brigade. I don't
care. Yeah. So, I'm just writing it all
down. And
then Frank says, "If all goes as
planned, we can be in Tehran by
August." And very discreetly, George
reaches reaches in front of him and
turns off his microphone. And he turns
to me and he says, "Did he say Baghdad
or did he say
Thrron?" And I said, "He said
Tehran." And George says, "Have these
people lost their minds?" And then he
turns his mic back on and he just sat
there. So at the end of the of the
meeting, I go back to the office and the
deputy director says to me, "How was the
principal committee?" And I said, 'D did
you know we were going to invade Iran?
And he said, 'Are they still talking
about that? We're not going to invade
Iran. I said, 'Do these people know
nothing about history? And he said, "No,
they know nothing about history." One of
these clowns from the NSC said as as
Cheney was wrapping up the meeting, he
said, "Tomorrow morning when we cross
the border, the Iraqi people are going
to throw flowers at us."
And I was like, they don't know anything
about history. Yeah. Or about the Middle
East.
As somebody who crossed the border right
after that and executed the number one
chemio target in Iraq, there were no
flowers
present at all.
Terrible.
God. And all you could do is shake.
Yeah, you know, you mentioned I I would
agree with you. I think at large the US
is
safer. What do you think about the
stability of the rest of the world? I
mean, we were so effective at find,
fish, find, fix, finish, exploit,
analyze that I actually, you know, at
first it started off with Taliban,
right, which in my opinion at least is a
a localized geographic gang at best, you
know, probably no, you know,
geopolitical.
Yeah. Al Qaeda, different story, but we
were so like, oh, two or three of you
get together, guess what? People with
night vision goggles are going to show
up. A 500 pounder is going to hit you.
That evolved to obviously, you know, a
guided missile off of a drone. And even
in my own experience, it became much
harder. They splintered. You know,
al-Qaeda became ISIS and it grew into I
think the last report I saw was 60 64
countries, something like that. Yeah.
Did we you know what do you think the
role of this fine fix finish we were so
good at it and also in that too there
was there was a lot of loss of life and
it's very I don't think you can fight
your way out of that ideology because I
think in the course of doing so uh
people who shouldn't die are going to
die and they're going to become
radicalized in that
approach how do you think our actions
specifically the US impacted stability
around the rest of the world oh I when
it came to just the permeation of
terrorism and those type of
interconnected I think we destabilized
uh a lot of the world uh by forcing this
this splinter for example ISIS that's
the easiest example ISIS was created
because a determination was made that
al-Qaeda wasn't radical enough it wasn't
violent enough and
Baghdaddy created ISIS while in a US
military prison in
Iraq. So, we almost forced it on them. I
remember, oh man, I remember a whole
bunch of us standing around a TV
watching George W. Bush in I think it
was December of 01. It had to be because
it was just before I left for Pakistan
in which he used the word nation
building and everybody groaned like,
"Oh, no, not nation. That means we're
going to be there for 20 years.
nation
building. The mission at the beginning
was to destroy al-Qaeda and we destroyed
al-Qaeda for all intents and purposes.
By by 2002, there were 25 known al-Qaeda
operatives left in Afghanistan. 25.
Yeah. We should have turned it over to
the drone corps and just let them finish
the
job. I really strongly believe that.
you know, paralleling over to because
again, we're looking a little bit in the
rearview mirror, 20 plus years at this
point. A lot of our strategy, bomb into
oblivion, target into oblivion. I look
over at things like Israel and Gaza, and
I'm just curious your thoughts. Well,
how do you think that plays itself out?
Because it's almost I don't want to say
it's an exact same template, but it's
it's not that different. Yeah. Yeah. I
I'm very very worried about Gaza for a
couple of reasons. First of all, you got
to call this a genocide. It meets the
legal definition of genocide quite
easily. Uh the forced removal, for
example, of a people, even if you don't
kill anybody, the forced removal is
genocide legally. Um, and then killing
civilians where where the Israeli
military acknowledges the Palestinian
health ministry's numbers of 90% of the
of the dead and wounded being civilians.
That's
genocide. You you you can't do that. But
nobody has either the guts or the
wherewithal to stop the Israelis from
doing it. Um, I think that the way this
works out is unless there is a real
change, a major change in foreign policy
among the Western countries, and I'm
including NATO, the EU, the United
States. Um, I think the Israelis going
to get away with it. I think the goal
for the Israelis
is the complete removal of Palestinians
from Gaza so that Israeli settlers can
can resettle the land and develop it. I
really believe that's what the case is.
And they they expect the Egyptians and
the Jordanians to take these
Palestinians. The Jordanians have said,
"Look, we're already 50% Palestinian.
We're not taking any more Palestinians."
And the Egyptians have just said, "Oh,
no, you're
not." The Gulf Arabs hate Palestinians.
They always have. That's why even after
all this, they're still willing to to
discuss normalization of diplomatic
relations with Israel. Saudi Arabia, the
land of the two holy mosques. It's
incredible to me. But they don't give a
[__] about
Palestinians, you know. And in the Gulf,
I I go to the Gulf with some frequency.
They're still angry that Yaser Arafat
sided with Saddam Hussein in
1990. You know, there's a price to pay
for that.
So, I I'm I'm worried that it's going to
get worse. Yeah. Those cultures have
long memories. Longer memories. Well,
they've also they've also existed far
longer than the US. I mean, I know we're
getting ready to celebrate 250. Pretty
big deal, you know. Y uh there's some
countries that are a culture a little
bit older than us. I mean, let's just
let's take it with a grain. I mean, 250
is good. Let's add a zero to that and
see how we're doing. If we can make it
that far, I worry and you know, with
that memory, God, I saw this in both
Iraq and Afghanistan. You know, people
would come in human and, you know, hey,
so and so, this is the guy you're
looking for. And, you know, we'd go
action the target and come to find out
three generations ago, a guy whatever
stole a goat or something like that.
That's a exactly
a rough example, but their memory
remains. I worry that that in that area
of the world, you know, just like Hamas
maybe being just absolutely pulverized
in Gaza right now, there's a real chance
that they are filling the ranks of Hamas
though in the long
just like the drone program did with us
or against us. I can't tell you how many
al-Qaeda fighters I interviewed who
couldn't find the US on a map. But man,
when we droned their village and killed
their uncle or their cousin or their
sister or whatever, they decided now's
now's the time for jihad. Where can
people find more of your work? Where can
they uh follow along in your journey?
Oh, thank you. Um, I publish everything
that I do on Substack. So, it's easy.
It's John
Kuryakustack.com. And I've got a couple
of podcasts myself. They're humble, but
one is Deep Focus with John Kuryaku. And
the other one is called Deprogrammed.
And finally, I've got a uh I've got a TV
show on an online uh uh channel called
Unified TV,
UnifyD, and the show is called uh CIA
declassified. We take newly declassified
original CIA documents and explain
historical events using those
documents. Hope you enjoyed today's
episode. Thank you again for listening
to Change Agents and Ironclad Original
presented by Firecracker Farm. I'll see
everybody next week with an all new
guest and an all new topic. See you
then.